be great but tell me tell me a bit I
mean you know we can meander through
everything I think that there will be in
an air of familiarity between us
yes just coming from the thought of
Heidegger and I I'm I did a PhD on
Heidegger that's so that's in that sense
I'm a scholar but I don't have a very
scholarly approach to Heidegger yeah
that's all I think and not to philosophy
I think this is also why academic
philosophy I mean to a certain degree
it's a necessary evil because you need
to go to a place and study really for
years and some people actually achieve
doing that outside of university I would
probably I'm not sure if I could or
could have done without an extended
period of just focusing on on one topic
but but then it just it circles around
itself right it's just it's another
machine that needs functioning it's just
it's a it's a it it is just you know the
term would be sure on that Heidegger
uses it it's just like standing reserved
yeah oh yeah what what all affected II
mean really turns into it is it's just
producing more for the sake of producing
more for it to be ready for use for why
because well because just because right
this is keep struggling around it and so
you know and I think in high to get
especially in hiding it he's like wanna
and stopped me if I talk too much right
but I think what do you get with hiding
is that he's born in the 19th century or
in a in a small town in southern Germany
and then these machines really moving in
to where he lives and sisa obviously the
the destruction right and Brussels or in
the Second World War so I think that's
why you have to take him quite you know
seriously he's not just he's he's sort
of almost like a memory of the old world
and then gets thrown into the the 20th
century in all of its horrors and he's
certainly not innocent
Marisha yeah yes kind of have I kind of
have a a similar feel because I'm I
think I'm one of the last generations
one of them I think that has it as a
memory before the internet yes and I
think that that's a memory is a good
word
yeah memories are very important I think
that memory or name alternate the
Mazzini I think you'd say in proper
English the Greek word for memory that's
in a strange way dying as we're
outsourcing it all to the Internet but
you you have a memory without the
internet you could even extend that to
saying what does it mean to have memory
without having an actual lived memory
that's then passed down but you know
because now if you don't know what how
to do something you just go online you
type into youtube how to watching
machine stuff it's it's useful it's not
actually but it's kind of there's the
strange thing in that I've read up a bit
on what your what do you as you put it
you've discovered it would you call
circling an interesting way of putting
it is to say if this counted rather than
saying I've invented it yeah come up
with a very different approach already
yes - to - to what do you do yeah it's
it's a and I think time and
temporalities is important and what in
what do you do right and when you're
trying to get across and what would the
internet does to a certain degree is
eradicate time but in a very strange way
it because time is still there the the
the the time of the internet is called
unix and it started somewhere in the
nineteen sometime in the 1970s and the
reason we can use this tool right now
you know line nine thirty here but it's
what one thirty Berkeley is because the
the Internet is actually completely
homogeneous yeah yeah it's and that's as
far as my understanding of that goes it
is it's too abstract for me but it's all
the manipulation that takes place online
or on screen is actually - certainly we
also related to time but it's no longer
human time or earthly time or anything
like it so there is something eerie
about yeah like hot like honking like
that sense of but but haunting in this
way that where I just notice where I can
still be scared of it yeah a lot of
people that are younger than me who are
quite strange characters right like like
really like literally like classic
autism good I don't know if they're
optimistic or not but what I think about
it yeah yeah where they when they speak
they're all they're all they're like
values are very articulated and
irrational and altruistic and explicit
and then they they speak literally in
like a screen opens up and they get
lines of information and analysis and
they're really bright but what's
interesting is they have done they don't
have they don't have any temporal
coordination in the relationship and
that's the thing I think you know one of
the things I think I'm understanding or
where part of my understanding or how I
am able to see like encircling or have
the particular way is house actually has
to do with Heidegger right yeah and I'm
understanding like because to read
Heidegger it's interesting for me it's
it's a real different kind of reading in
my experience because it's not so much
about I know this like it's not so much
about understanding what he's saying but
it's more oxime to be a what it takes to
attempt to understand him
yeah and there's something about that
I think for me that yoga stretch or that
stepping so up outside or actually not
outside but so into the background right
to then look and to try to understand
that motion over and over and over and
over again all of a sudden I just
started to like see backgrounds and
foregrounds and were temporalities and
like and then language would just come
out of that right yeah yeah yeah I think
yeah so that's being in time that the
experience of reading being in time or
is it yeah and I being in time in an end
and his other work too and a lot of
people I've read a lot of people who've
written about his work as well hmm right
now I'm like diving into the young
Heidegger which who's that but all day
young Heidegger it's um office right
here but I but it's well I just think
it's fascinating how deeply he was
looking at is in his younger years like
this is the lately I've gotten kind of
infected by his younger when he was
younger yeah how deeply he was in to
like the Christian mystics you know
Ekans and and a lot of these like deeply
theological thinkers and how he kind of
took a lot of them and ontology it in a
certain sense and it's interesting
because it was in its in kind of
understanding that more right yeah I
mean instead I just bought a bunch of
his ol is his actual earlier works I
haven't told them to him yet
but that's reading that it's funny I'm
understanding I think a lot more
especially around temporality and how
primordial it is yeah yeah that sense of
that sense of the future kind of you
could say kind of the future going to
the past and into the present right like
it doesn't go future present past it
like it's the sense of yeah it's in this
is why hee hee hee in in in the Chairman
he wouldn't speak of a garden hide on
his ends and too closed he calls the
garden had would be in English past he
speaks of it as having been given height
and I think the English grammatical form
he brings it out quite well but what has
been still lingers on yeah like I have
been doing this forever have been doing
this I've been reading Heidegger for so
many years now that means there's
something that lingers from the past and
it isn't and and then the there is there
is a sense of presence in high ticket
but it is not not this presence of say
often of the perfect consumption
consumer society we live in where we are
and they always trapped in a certain
presence but that presence is you know a
presence with immediacy in that they
just react to certain things but that
good presence comes about as he
ecstatically so it's a standing out into
at the same time of standing back into
and it's it's so and the future true
cold in German you can you know he reads
this as saying it's coming towards ya
so there's design is in a dozen in terms
just means presence and existence and be
there being right being there design and
design is not some kind of a homunculus
like it's it's not properly you or I or
any kind of an abstract way of
describing the human being design just
means that the way we are and so it
that's why me means by by being right
it's it's always it's this activity that
then we are right like what seems they
really say something way way and you
always I mean this is why the hands come
in because words themselves don't fully
express it but that which comes towards
us from that which has been right
properly then if doesn't but death is
very important is we can talk about that
at some point but surely in purely
structural terms that which has been
it's coming towards us from that which
will be and that forms the presence but
at the same time that which is to come
isn't just you know coming from behind
as it were just from what has been there
are always also so you could say bubbles
and being a new hujrat new horizons yeah
being torn open and and heard I mean for
example one of hiding his most beloved
poets speaks also of time tearing open
new horizons so in that sense you know
as you put it time is primordial yeah I
miss oddly primordial but the way we
been before Heidegger it's it's always
in the in being in time I think you put
it well when you said you know I'm gonna
paraphrase you that it isn't Theory it
is he's not trying to have any test in
several times that I'm not producing
anything he's actually just ask when
there are these hints that he gives
there's always footnotes and all of his
text for example in being in times very
interesting footnote when he says that
Aristotle's what it what's it what's it
translated as I think the oratory off
you know which is usually it's
considered to be a book about speaking
about how to give a speech how to give a
talk so it's a theory about how you give
a talk in hiding he says that's nonsense
it is actually an hermeneutical analytic
or diagnosis of the air of everyday life
so he reads all of philosophy about how
do we mean he doesn't use the word but
how do we live how
we exist and then it becomes encrusted
over time and taken to be timeless the
truth truthful propositions of them
tested against the logical necessity and
coherence etc when he's trying to break
free from all of that and saying look
what but they were trying to say
something else entirely he's trying to
back to that from within a master
Western framework which of course always
already falls back into that you know
philosophy being institutionalized and
scholarly etc especially with the 19th
century that's coming up but so
structurally you have all of this and to
a certain degree you know you can also
read then design in that sense not just
you yourself in your own memories and an
origin and birth and thoroughness but
history in its entirety yeah it's always
already sweeping back slowly like in in
coming back in waves and crashing it
because before Heidegger he said we are
the locust of history but that that
doesn't mean that we are like so a
humanist to speak very properly a
humanistic or humanist understanding of
history would mean that we are the
ancients of history right we make
everything like we can hack the brain
and then just put a new app in it bla
bla bla
no that's not what he means it means
that we are you know extremely fragile
and qua finite beings we are the place
of history because it breaks out within
our temporalities in memory and but but
for being in time what what the book is
I think trying to say is that you cannot
have one without the other and that
means you cannot have the authentic way
of being which is in this state it's a
way of being again without the unit
entik one is never without the other
just like disclosure or um concealment
or openness more nearness cannot be
without absconded absalom needle yeah
Andy that's a good one isn't it yeah
yeah yeah being absconds I think for
high together that's what it does and
then it comes back so oh and that you
cannot have one without the other you
cannot have total concealment sorry you
can't have total unconsumed
you can have total disclosure because
every every disclosure every moment of
disclosure is structured fundamentally
by concealment hiding actually in it my
hope hope hope I hope I'm not
paraphrasing him too much for that in a
letter to father Richardson he says time
if being is you know being that means
presence unreason that that which is
there and open but time is that which
okay the time is that which by time is
that which self conceals and structures
that very presence yeah this is why the
title being and time is not an additive
is not being here in time here it's it's
almost like one word right being time
it's one word it but it but it needs to
have the end because the end is it's not
you know 1+1 yes but it's it's you could
you cannot think what he means by being
without what he calls time how he thinks
time works and the way I think within
being in time you you enter you can and
send this sounded like this was your
experience over the years of reading
this so then opens something up right
there it isn't about okay I'm gonna
memorize this right then I'm gonna argue
oh this is actually wrong um because
it's developmental and it breaks
something open yes like it frees
something yes and I think in historical
terms of hiding it either consciously or
not I wouldn't care he's doing is he's
freeing us from the matrix of
cartesianism we're retracting our brains
and within our own minds you know yeah I
hacked the brain and then I mean this is
literally where the idea of I think off
the cloud which is a neo Gnosticism
right I just all I have to do is get rid
of the prison of the flash and then I
can think about myself and live forever
freely in the
out which is Google's plan ultimately so
that there has to took Gnosticism into
Descartes and so hiding is trying to
free us from that subject object economy
where the world is just an object to me
right an object of use of manipulation
something that's present at hand as he
calls it for hunting but I can relate
which is modern subjectivity or
subjectivism in a nutshell yes he's
trying to say no what you are is a
finite being thrown into the world there
is no distinction between you know the
eye and the foul in that sense yeah and
and and I think what ultimately the the
book is doing because hiding is
approaching is the transformation of the
human being if I'm and alone was
mentioned is to be pushed you know
you're pushed towards death yeah being
in time what you're ultimately always
facing is your own death and that's why
he calls it as a very strange way of
putting it your own most possibility it
gives you nothing to actualize and
that's painful for the modern subject
because the modern subject the modern
human being must actually wear you know
look at look at like any kind of like
any advertisement as pretty to say any
advertisement right will be for fulfill
your potential or we are unlimited
potential that's all metaphysical
language for Heidegger yes to a certain
degree we are potential and we are
possibility move this fight but we're
also ultimately bound up and limited by
a possibility that that is our most
authentic possibility that gives us
nothing to actualize and that is a
tension that is all it is nearly
unbearable for the mother subject but he
says this is what we have to push the
human being towards in modernity because
this is what's lacking and this is why I
think you know not only not that this is
why but one of the
you could look at in more detail at the
structural reasons for example why is it
that Silicon Valley is trying to
eradicate death great because it gives
them nothing to actualize because death
is the last realm that cannot be
measured it's a round thing once you
think of death has a realm and I'm
saying a lot now I know once you think
of it as a realm as I mention it always
already into a certain degree but but it
gives us nothing to this just nothing
right and that nothingness though is of
course as Heidegger puts it very active
but the nothing neither lace yes totally
and nothing to actualize isn't like an
necessarily like an absence like but
it's an actual quote it's a terms of the
quality or it's the way things presents
like so like to act to actualize nothing
is is actually not just negative right
it's like yeah what in I guess the
question is in actual izing nothing what
is what is it that gets actualized when
I actualize the nothing is there but
sorry I don't
you don't actualize the nothing because
there's nothing it's like there there is
this utter limit yeah been pushed
against oh yeah right there like I could
just feel in myself
I don't want there to be a limit you
know think of modern subjectivity as
always right so I'm gonna make this you
mean no offense but you're an American
Americans are all about making the
impossible possible yes
making America great again going to the
moon I'm not just an American I'm a
Midwestern boy yes we know what it's
like we you know the frontiers there it
is
it's very manic to be honest it's it's
there's something admirable about it
there's nothing wrong with it
there is this limit that there is death
that that always already is as soon as
we are four Heidegger the end and and
there is nothing there you can access by
but but to leave you know a bit around
the nothing itself without you having to
do anything is active
that's what how do you guess it does
nice nice tit
there's the nothing nine lights and the
snitch them is is a verbal form that
doesn't exist in German that's true but
we do have a verb mature which is hadn't
eaten so that mitten means to destroy to
distract to the certifies of the world
to make something to utterly obliterate
right so the the it's and and you you
can think of the human being is always
walking on the edge between the nothing
and and being and both of them are
active in an interplay and and one
cannot be without the other and what you
perceive so say say for example think of
a thing thing with very practical
example maybe you choose to to choose to
follow a certain path in your life that
is only possible by in that sense then
eradicating other possibilities that you
could have followed always you're always
also a great destroyer yeah that then is
the utter responsibility that you have
as a human being is not to become an
obliterator
right this is what people like ester a
power as for a pound in in in his main
work and the name of the title eludes me
just now says to be men not destroyers I
think that's what he means but that
Nietzsche says in the prologue to seven
through straw do or at least in Cyprus
for somebody where those who bear
deserts within themselves so you because
we're always already on the edge
between being a nothingness I mean
there's nothing you know in middle of
itself that's wrong with that but we can
become extremely destructive forces if
you like right so and and for Heidegger
I think we are is even more destructive
if we don't face up to death I said it
gives us nothing to actualize which
means that that's just this you you hit
a brick wall you hit a wall that you but
once I think what what he calls running
forth towards death
pushing or anticipating death is
ultimately and in in reading being in
time for example and exercise if you
like a spiritual exercise where the
experience of ecstatic temporalities
becomes possible and that's a totally
different way of being with and in time
then the way we are you know I will
usually and think of time yes and we
have to and we have to think of time to
go about our day which is its whatever
time now and it's all linear time passes
right but fatigue I think ecstatic time
doesn't pass it arises right and as it
arises it gives way so it's a constant
gifting and giving anybody giving it's
like is it because one of the things
I've noticed about about just just when
you go and just find yourself like you
look down and you're already begun like
like when I go and kind of go alright so
where am I the where has already begun
and everything like that
the ecstatic awareness of it is somehow
or already has arisen and I'm somehow I
think that this this sense of the one
the one who does become aware yeah has
this quality of illness already it's
already begun like I can't get behind
myself and push myself forward which i
think is like a lot of
it seems like a lot of American kind of
psychological stuff is has this kind of
presupposition that like you can kind of
create yourself you can see and push
yourself out yeah there's a deep
embeddedness is that is that what you're
talking about is that the core is that
kind of an aspect or starts to get in
the way of the quality of time is is it
it it comes kind of from the bottom up
yeah the bottom up yeah it works through
you to a certain degree it is you my god
is this like death that's why he says
you know original time is finite yeah
there's no times designs temporality
that doesn't mean that we are the center
of the universe it just means that the
way we are is so fundamentally
ecstatically temporal right he could not
have abstract from it and the example
you just gave is you know is although is
frightening on the one hand but it's
also just on point because what that
assumes like create yourself and you
know everyday with it you know to
certain degree it's quite French if you
want to throw and Sean Paul you call him
saath saath wit from Paul right to a
certain degree says exactly that yeah
right he says that existence comes
before essence and that means that Ness
comes before Watson as' and almost from
a nominal to speak in the content term
what Roman numerals fear which is
timeless and only accessible to certain
part of human reason can you then posit
yourself your own that that you are
which is existence and from that move on
to whatever you want to be right I mean
so it's even it's even worse it's just
you you you make yourself um not sure I
mean this is why I start the scientist
reading of hiding it's just so
completely misguided because he
that leads Heidegger and then and then
one of the most brilliant mistakes and
philosophy it seeks yes you know and
very modern so he is very modern reading
of Heidegger and hiding it just wanted
to something else entirely
we just you were thrown this is why he
speaks of give orphan high right balance
thrown into the world yes and that means
you haven't decided to be here yes you
know what no one asks you to be born
no one asked me to be born and we were
never asked do you want to have these
parents these are they okay you know
most most people some people might say
you know but so you have so you didn't
choose that he didn't choose what he
look like you didn't choose anything to
certain degree yeah you didn't choose
some language he were born into and the
language makes up the way the world
opens up to you yes
you didn't chose the epoch you literally
throw in through the world and you're
trying to make sense of what's going on
but the the modern way of going about it
is in the one hand we are in charge
anyways yeah and we're like I'm like a
lab Ninian monad that's just all
consuming and devouring I mean it's very
interesting that in modernity you get
you know the will is very important the
cannot vez that's what the Latin word
for it and Spinoza's like a never
devouring will the the monad which is
almost like a you know a single
substance just to itself there's many of
them for it for life as an incident
amount but still it's all devouring it's
always has appetite and you know you did
this is stretching it a bit but we're
not speaking a scholarly here so I'll
just be know extremely experimental I I
sometimes think off Guns'n'Roses record
Appetite for Destruction and like a
postmodern response to the Enlightenment
hopes off of someone like lightness
right because for live events the
appetite is is important we see a patek
for our perception right so for for
recognizing the world and seeing the
world and taking it all in and then
universalizing everything in
systematizing the whole the whole
universe and then making sense of it all
that's that's kind of what this polymath
is after good old like it's and then in
post modernity you get to some obscure
band that for no obvious reason speaks
of Appetite for Destruction I mean
there's still appetite but now it's just
an appetite for it
you know we've categorized everything
we're kind of we're done with that what
are we gonna do now
let's blow it all up I mean this is
pushing it a bit right because that's
not all that happens but there is to a
certain degree that the postmodern
reaction the reaction of people like
daily Don for calling others and to to
the enlightenment is really to go and
say we don't need any categories we you
can rid of all of that which has its own
you know terrible consequences you know
what do you think that they miss like
the the dairy does and like the proposed
and they're really like well what they
miss is that what they are trying to do
is if you if you want to yeah what
they're trying to do on their own terms
is not even possible because if if
you're telling me there's no grand
narrative and you're working with you
know against logos if you like and
you're working against truth and there's
nothing there there's no there then I
don't have to listen to you because if
all you're telling me is that there's
literally nothing and nothing nothing
nothing
then and then people will be outraged
you know if he publishes because there
was I don't know is actually look he
just has a very good critique of
neoliberalism so yes and Foucault does
have that yeah but you can always have
critique I mean what's so astonishing
about modernity as well is everyone's a
critic
I mean look there's structural reasons
why these critical systems like you know
Google evaluations and TripAdvisor
whatever
everyone's a food critic now but there's
nothing psychological about that there's
something structural about that the
reason is that modernity itself or post
learn see it's just criticism for the
sake of criticism of batik was a routine
and when hiding it does is something
else where he doesn't keep - certainly
yes he critiques modernity if you like
yes but he gives you a solution I mean
not not a solution one fits all but it's
it's uh it's exits like there are ways
out and those aren't exactly in time
like exactly in yes as you put it I once
when you read this you realize oh I can
actually like I can't actually abstract
from everything that is I and then leap
back into whatever I want but it's
always already working through me coming
yeah you know what washing up against
Smith however you want to put it itself
yeah like I can't ever get the
background to the floor like like no
yeah yeah I get the back be rid of the
background right which whatever because
without background no foreground
exactly and that's kind of ecstatic
structure right if you will I don't know
if the structure is the right word but
like yeah that said I mean look I think
of it as a I you have to try to make
sense of things in your own words right
yeah
so the structure is I think fine you
could think of it as a structure ring
yes it's always red all always already
in motion
yeah yeesh on that that's very important
always already means that you haven't
chosen yourself because there's
something always already working through
it's always already you are always
already thrown you're always already
being towards death and you know and the
thing is you're weird towards death
anyways yeah yeah um and then but then
it's not a willful choice to say okay
I'm gonna be running first towards my
death and just accepted well I think
there's this something it's it is a so
it's not morbid or or or a reduction
to death but or to immortality but what
Heidegger wants or wishes that once
which is us to do asks us to maybe ask
us to do is to let go and to let go
means that you and that so that's that
there's it's not a leap in the sense of
you walk towards a certain cliff then
you see the necessity to leap down into
something yeah he he lets I asked him
the leap that happens in his in that
must happen in this thinking is a
letting go of anything familiar and once
that happens you let go of with you know
beings that signs of everything that is
graspable right don't you don't you you
cannot fall back to these metaphysical
expertise also being is just reality OB
is just an ultimate Oh being is just God
no being is and that that's the later
Heidegger to leap into the Terek text
that's being is what he calls a
vagueness to a certain degrees is that
that which that that which as it comes
into its own withdraws and absconds and
but but that's at one simultaneous and
this is something that you might not
have heard yet because these are very
obscure tax I'm just going to mention it
Heidegger begins to call death the
mountain range of being and the way yeah
so in the Trevon word and this is is
gonna make little little sense to anyone
is for for mountain ranges get big which
which hiding understands and this is not
etymologically correct or anything but
he understands that as the concentration
or gathering of sheltering harboring
concealment so because there's the verb
balgan in hippie like if you he hears
it's it's probably not really there but
that's what he hears in it anyway and so
you can think of if death is the
mountain range of being and we are
mortals and finite beings
then what the history of being is and
how it works is that we are you know if
you think of a mountain range the
mountain mountains are extremely
powerful phenomena for human beings I
mean at least they should be in our
desolate age now you have traffic jams
up on up on Mount Everest I don't know
if you see the pictures but it's it's if
everything's become so available that
that nothing has any you know any missed
any
there's no miss struggle anymore hey
yeah okay yes yeah no struggle no no
mysticism nothing that's yeah hatred
yeah right
nothing sacred left so but but while you
but if you think of still if you know in
a different plane maybe the Mount
Mountains are nearly inaccessible and
they are inaccessible to a large degree
still I mean you it's just it and
there's valleys you can get lost people
you know it's it's there's something
there's something in that sense that's
always self concealing with mountains
yeah and I think what would he kind of
like this is kind of like when that like
phenomenologically when you look up at a
mountain yeah they're just there's no
immediate way to get over that mountain
in that moment it's like it tops you if
you will right like the quality of I'm
imagining what Heidegger means is
something like even when if I live in
that village is under the mountain and
even when I'm not looking at the
mountain somehow that mountain gives the
ground in which things occur and arise
as they do yeah and I think that there's
what you know it's funny when I was a
kid you know Illinois was really flat
land and and I lived in the suburbs and
I always felt this kind of like nos
llegan
a nauseous vacant like empty parking lot
feeling I guess all I can talk call is
like that nobody that's very good
putting it because a parking lot is not
a place yeah yes yes a parking lot is
ultimately I mean this is what's again
the strangeness of modernity and how do
you go speaks of our epoch as an e-book
that's estranging us a parking lot has
lacks everything that I mean that the
burbs isn't cool right if they're just
extended parking lots a people are
parked right just like just like in you
know in the 50s and 60s is hideous
towers went up and they're still going
up of course the mountains would I don't
know what you call the manglers freeways
yeah no I mean these deceivers we a
skyscrapers but not just I mean look the
Empire State Building that's like a
neoclassical building I mean these
hideous buildings in the Soviet Union
and yeah they're just people
optional yeah what what's the technical
term for these I'm not familiar with
ones I just called it but you know
thousands of people call it hell Oh
apples
yeah hell escapes yes up until this date
not livable I mean I'm in London right
now very very close to where I am
somewhere in East London there are these
hideous towers and they were
purposefully built as ugly to prove a
point there now you know this is
complete hellscape so you know high
crimes
hundreds of people crammed in City one
of these blocks there and it's it's just
terrible but um I think just to finish
this one one point on on death as being
them up that's the mountain range of
being and the history of being if you
think of us as mortals I think what
hiding is trying to say is if we are
then it took me years to say understand
is to strike we are striding through a
history that is like a mountain range
and that's what he calls death it's it's
this that's a concealment all the time
we can hope
is these rare moments of seeing you know
seeing the peak and as you've described
it right in finding a ground finally I
think you put it like they were finding
your ground letting letting something
occur in and off itself so that we can
find a plateau way to live on and then
move on etc and and this is the
experience of what it means to be human
and respond to that I think for
Heidegger and and what we're doing of
course is you know and then maybe if you
want to make that leap in in thought
then perhaps the traffic jams off I'm
American I'm already I'm ready to leap
you know maybe the the thousands of
people now hiking up yeah on Everest
like it means nothing just another thing
you consume because something to take
off right tells you that it's not much
left so I mean that if everything's
being made that available yes and and
present at hand then what we're dealing
with is it's really just the the planet
becoming an amusement park for for a
very bored as you you know we had a
short exchange yesterday on YouTube
there and on board nosov boredom it's
like why is this happening why why would
you even do it if it's not an
achievement it's because there is this
achievement of boredom that then leads
to this mood of boredom and on the on
the parking lot I think that's a great
example is how we are building as world
building beings non places cuz the lead
we know we meet we make that but why do
we make them why do we build them why do
we build places that are any places yeah
let lack everything that make a place
and what's a plate I mean a place for
asar is the des hundreds of people maybe
thousands of people that are suburb
right but there's no community yes yes
yeah it's like
where is the gathering point where is
the where the name meets wait where is I
mean yes you have megachurches who you
can go into Sunday because why not
but or the McDonald's or what not which
is where the you I mean I remember when
I first came to North America 12 years
ago I spent some time in Vancouver right
and I remember the youths sitting in the
in the burbs sitting on McDonald's on a
Sunday right that was literally the only
place where they could go yeah yeah yes
but where's the gathering right and what
where do we come together right right
like there's that we're at least in the
older cities have noticed in the u.s.
the older cities there's such a
different feeling in the older cities
then yeah like then like say you know
Phoenix is like Phoenix La La's yeah its
own universe but yeah like well because
one of the things that in older cities
in America you know you could say that
you know they're not even old compared
to Europe I mean I don't even think we
have any sense of like idea I know what
I went to when I went and started
leading courses in Europe yeah walking
bah I was just like driving down the
road and looking at you know there'd be
this look like a thousand years old or
something right of just this built-up
building that's been there forever with
like a maybe an addition built on to it
and people are just walking by as if
yeah I'm not into me it was just like I
had no Drock that you know it's like
greenhouses are like ancient yeah but
the but there's such a different feeling
and I think it's kind of probably what
what Heidegger and what you're kind of
getting at I think as in there's a sense
of place where because the the old
because a city would converge with the
railroads so it's like as the railroads
would all converge it would get
more concentrated right and then right
where it converged was like the most
concentrated part of the city in the
sense of time right where everything's
kind of built on top of each other and
you have these layers of different kinds
of buildings and they're like they have
to adjust to themselves and it's like
it'd be a the city of merges right and
then that there's a sensibility with a
lot of them others like a town square
there's like a center right with a
church or like a park around it and it's
like everything you can get this quality
of like emergence out of yeah yeah where
my son my son lives in Plano Texas which
is just absolutely the worst I could be
there for about three days and after
that I like I either need to take like
lots of prozac or I gotta get out of
there um but they literally they they
built a town yeah is and it was you
could tell it was for a certain kind of
consumer so everything right is built
for the consumer yep and it is come it's
like a completely different place to be
yeah and everything's ina like is
ordered right is accessible huh but but
I think that that's not you know it's
not I mean that's you know sad yeah and
but it isn't an American problem
I would not you know all that a world
problem because I think what's happening
and I mean yes you have because you know
cities start somewhere they have a heart
right there usually so for example my
city is called my hometown is called
Alex book which means the castle of
Augustus Augustus was a Roman Empire mmm
Emperor who seventeen before Christ
fifteen before Christ when ever camped
where we now have Augsburg up on a hill
obviously because that makes sense to
the Opera Hills you can get attacked
that around that original camp and he
tried to breach into jimana further and
take the rest of the the region
therefore for the Roman Empire which
didn't really happen that all the time
became a focal point and then slowly
developed and it develops organically
but it takes time again we're back to
time right in our age we don't take time
it's just as you say you know it's like
that place in Texas is built for its
it's it's but it's built for what it's
not built for you could say so the camp
was set up by Augustus to have a base
from where he could branch out into the
woods and then take the lands from the
originally too tramatic tribes then it
became something else it became it
attracts tradesmen it attracts craftsmen
because wherever there's power and
political power that's money as of it
attracts and then it free
I wouldn't know the reasons because I'm
not a historian but the camp remained
and it was built up and it became a city
but that takes time maybe 50 years maybe
a hundred years and then slowly it grows
over now it's a two thousand-year-old
settlement right where and there's one
of the sensations I had when I lived in
Seattle eight years ago for about six
months was that this is the I had the
very clear feeling this is and I lived
in Capitol Hill which is very very
central you know I thought that this is
the this is wilderness and the trees
look wild to compare to the trees in
Europe I felt like animals like foxes
and one hurling around at night yeah but
I saw them and they looked at me like
you have no idea what's going on here
because it is all so new it's
that's how I felt when I to Europe I
thought okay now I'm walking on ground
again huh
walking I have this substance I mean Oh
Heidegger and shouldn't speak of
substance but anyway so there was there
was a ground again but I will say this
about you know the American experience
is that you are free from metaphysics
and that you know it leads to these
hideous like McDonald's KFC gas station
shopping mall Walmart and then you drive
into town and everything's dead you
drive out again but at the same time
that freedom also has a certain hat is
is a freedom also in a you know in a
positive sense it gives you an openness
to ways of thinking you know that that
then hiding it might be after as well so
it isn't you know it always comes in
there's not it's never just but you
cannot have peace without or like you
cannot have just as well and just as
variety gets always freedom is always
unfreedom and just to mention this in
our age I think and this epoch the task
of the human being is to withold
withstand live the freedom that we
experience in terms of technology coming
in and things being extremely weird and
strange to anyone who's awake everyone
else is you know kind of lost anyways
what's happening in Europe though is
it's not so what you're describing there
it's not just something American and I'm
not going to make a political point of
saying oh oh the American Empire is just
reaching out therefore it doesn't
McDonald's everywhere yeah but it's
there must be an openness to in Europe
to want something like that because we
have these suburbs as well that are
faceless right they don't even have a
proper facade there's just there are
places in like Venice Beach works of
limit and then in LA that have much more
of a feel of place than many of the new
newly built and recently built last 30
40 years or so in Germany for example of
suburbs that are
really dead and they're all just there
to park people when they come back from
their nine-to-five and and then you know
do the routine of television or whatever
else you have to do it to be the perfect
you know the consumer yes that that's
what we are obviously we recalled
consumers right I mean fabric alpha is
like a normal which is consumer is a
normal regular term used by politicians
right listen row and there's something
else look at look at a place like London
London is another 2,000 year old Roman
settlement and of course it's have a
real history there was a huge fire and
some time in early modern times and it
was destroyed by Nazi bombings in the
Second World War but it it always sort
of maintained its its uniqueness but
what's happening now I said there are
skyscrapers going up everywhere and
there are they're not beautiful
buildings like the Empire State Building
because the Empire State Building is you
know classical it's a certain degree
architecture yeah but it's just these
and I don't think that's a question of
taste it's that there's something else
happening here there's something else
showing itself it's just glass and steel
and concrete right so and one of them
and I've mentioned this in another
conversation event with Justin Murphy
it's also up on YouTube so I'm just
repeating myself but I'm just gonna say
anyway is that there's one building
called maybe you've heard of it called
the shard yeah a shard so it's a shot
it's literally a shard that you break
glass and you have a chance right and it
looks unfinished
it looks like a dystopian techno version
of the evil eye that Sargon or whatever
it's called
Sauron alone I think it is yeah for the
Rings yes Mike because it's got these
hideous red lights so the you know
airplane some crash crash into it right
but it is a shard it cuts so it's unfit
looks like it's unfinished yes and it
cuts into the sky cuts into the sky
that's how I interpreted you know I look
at it and it just literally cuts into
the sky but who lives who inhabits the
sky its gods its immortals yeah right so
it's all its it why is this I mean you
know you could always say it's just some
idiot architect but if it isn't just
about subjective psychological it made
sense yeah there there's something
there's something that in a terrible in
a in a very terrible way makes sense for
this epoch yes then it would happen now
that you would that build a temple in
honor of Apollo or a church right in
honor of the Christian God or a
synagogue an order of honor of Yahoo
mosque in that sense but no you build
the building called the shard that is
the tallest building up until this day
in Western Europe and that cuts into for
the sky and in that sense is you know is
meaningfully destructive but that's
what's it's that's what the purpose is
right and it has that there's nothing
beautiful about it except that all it is
it's tall it's really tall so it did
this there's this yeah and I mean I
think you know if that strangeness can
you imagine another epoch where where
anyone would have built a building
that's called the shard cutting into
something into yeah what why is that
yes that's hideous it's just absurd but
you know pointing this out to people
will get you looks can I can I ask you
something so like a little bit I'd love
to hear um so just first of all like I
really appreciate it like appreciate
really appreciated all your videos and
in there
there's a something and I don't know if
I can describe it but there's a there's
a way in which you speak about these
things and in it it reveals of a being
deeply touched by it like there's like
wait as you're talking these you can't
get the sense of high level of
abstractions although they are in some
respect
there's your like grappling with it
feels like it's coming from deep in you
like it's almost like I asked you a
question and we're just like you've
already been thinking about you were
just thinking about it or something
there's something a sense of wrestling
with something and being touched by it
or moved by it like what what is your
experience of what's your personal
experience of the philosophy and how do
you you if it does and like what what
about it at reduce would deeply like
before like when did you start for
example like when did you start reading
Heidegger yeah like what was life like
before that and after that I it's a very
you know it's a very important question
I guess I couldn't let me answer with
Hegel and then I'll I'll talk about
myself Hegel somewhere says in him
paraphrasing him then the the
philosopher dies every day from worry we
could the philosopher worries about the
about the world and and there's
something if I could have distanced
myself from myself for a minute there is
something I'm very aware of myself I
have I think an extreme self-awareness
in terms of what my thinking is some of
my experiences the philosophy for me
isn't intellectual I can get into all
this intellectual douchebaggery and I'm
very good at you know look I'm looking
at this argument taking it apart but yes
that there's something that that's you
don't come across as an intellect you
come across as the living it or
it's it's close to you you're grappling
yeah it is closing its it that's yes and
it's always been close I mean one of the
things I yeah I was not very good at
school reason being what's cool is like
supportive that's whatever you know in
Germany you go to elementary school
which is just four years and then they
rip you up into three different classes
you can go to the lowest school which is
called main school hub truly or the
middle school the Alex really real
school interesting name or or the given
bottom which is the highest form you you
know like ten years old when you you
mean you get you know grouped up this
huge burden and stress on parents and on
the child if you make it or not
blah blah blah but I remember that I
wanted to go to a so cultural meniscus
collosseum a humanistic in math you
would think the the British call grammar
school so we you'll learn Latin and
ancient Greek rather than something you
can use right Spanish spending today
it's Spanish and Chinese yes that's
something you can use like language is
not something you use right it's that oh
look I'm just gonna look this is why you
get this is language is where we live
and now it's not a tool you know I'm
just gonna learn some English tonight no
I mean if the language and get a feeling
for it and I think this is why I can get
across all of this in a foreign non
native language because I'm trying to
enter that house that is the English
language so I'm trying to speak from
within the language itself and and I had
it was mine or so I had
very clear idea that if I learn Latin
and ancient Greek and I would gain
access to the mysteries of the world I
have no idea where this is coming from
why I had this idea because there was
certainly I mean yes my parents you know
read a lot and I have to I have four
Greek names
yeah Johannes and Leah's hemicycle Yanis
is like a Greek version of I think it's
a great version of a Hebrew name but I
don't know why but that that kind of
that idea was with me when I was very
young and I I went to this school and it
was the exact opposite right it was just
learning the grammar by heart aloha and
it took me years of suffering until I
had one good teacher who actually lost
the ancient Greek language so much that
I turned from a really bad student of
pupil to really good understanding of
the language and so I read all of the I
you know the pre-socratics as we
categorize him now in the Platonic
dialogues and homers a great great works
and and and and Aristotle to a certain
degree as well so I read all of this in
the original there's there's a certain
there was always and and I always had
the best understanding of Plato and of
Heraclitus those were closest you had a
very hard time translating everything so
I I couldn't translate but I didn't
understand Riesling
but in and then it but it's this kind of
like you know I think there's something
about the Philosopher's that there's
always a certain feeling of a strange
meant with everyone else
yeah and I've always had that right but
it's and then I came to to
two pods on where I studied philosophy
politics and economics and a wonderful
teacher who is also not you know an
intellectual but he lives he lives this
way of thinking because that that's what
it is and then it all came back that
this kind of thing they do because it's
covered you know it was kind of it was
gone for a while man I had left school
and but it came back and ever since then
which is now ten years ago I've been on
this very clear trajectory of having to
go deeper and deeper and deeper there's
a there's something pulling me you know
it's not like I'm not exhausted
yeah right it's very late it's very late
you're like I could tell yeah it's it's
a pole if you like that's how people
describe it it's it's it's something
that just it opens up anyway so I don't
have to left yeah it's there it's just
fully there I don't know why but it's
there and it's always been there and
it's it's now it's thanks to Heidegger I
know
thanks to Eva this novel was the
professor and Italy where I was and
other people that I've met just reading
that it it all is it all kind of has
come about right but it but it's always
but it feels like in in that sense of
amor fati that it's always been
necessary so I bet that's why it's it's
not it's not work I'm not this is not
excruciating or painful or get me off I
need to eat or sleep no I just like
looking up and everything else is
mundane and and and kind of painful but
this isn't and and and I had to and this
is this I mean I have this is gonna
sound extremely strange I was in mess
kill two years ago for the first time
which is hyda cos hometown
and I think one of his and he's got two
sons and one of them is his actual son
Northam it's not his son he just raised
him as his son yeah and his actual son I
think was there or maybe the son of his
son I'm not sure but one of his
relatives was there who's you know
related siding her properly and if when
I talk to him he's very old he it seemed
like he knew me he thought he knew me
because it was not because it was his
Terrace is familiarity right there's the
Ameli arity that that that's beyond the
time that could probably also happen but
if you met some other hundred years ago
who have that kind of thinking as well
yeah yeah that makes any sense but there
is there's often the feeling yet
familiar and I think this is why it is
this weird world we live in where you
stumble on some obscure video yeah so
and and yeah but it's not theory that
that's I mean it is theory proper
because the areia means to live to
actually try and live it and make sense
of the world not in this it yes it's
abstract to a certain degree and you
need to actually be very very strict and
need to be able to think in abstract
terms and prevent it like I think what
what my talent may be is is to make it
understandable accessible without
turning it into not not too accessible
right it shouldn't be too clear or too
easy because then it just becomes
nothing again but I but but what it is
and why there is this pull I don't know
but I can't if if I would I couldn't
stop yeah I'm looking back it's always
been like this I go to bold sound for no
reason like literally I mean I met a guy
who was in Augsburg accidentally right
he tells me that there's the study
program at this obscure you know
ten-year-old University in bored sauna
but that no one ever goes to yeah it's
not a special now it's a special place
back then no one knew about it and then
there's this gentleman you would hnr for
who is teaches Heidegger the way he
wants he doesn't care what other people
say he doesn't care about anything and
and for for some reason it all left me
there and so he said I mean it I don't
know if you have the time there's a
video of of me and him on the channel oh
is that the guy that we're he's talking
about the essence of Technology yeah
yeah oh yeah he was something it isn't
what about like three times yeah cuz he
yeah he said he he made Joe for me like
a bunny yeah the whole thing about the
hit I think I finally understood what
Heidegger meant by history history yeah
and in the new beginning that's not that
was always like a stop strange weather
is so elusive like a new beginning but
that's that sense of going back and
looking at content and looking at
Aristotle and this sense of the way that
he described I really appreciated it
like that there were terms that they
took but they didn't take these other
terms and you can they're in there in
the kind of the atmosphere right of the
terms that they took but there's a
background there yeah listens into the
concealment and then and then tries to
tries to let let it show right and I was
like oh that's what he okay okay that's
what he means by new beginning it's
Jenny Heidegger says these things where
like Ivan like um
clicks it doesn't click like you know
it's a little bit like uh trying to
remember remember a dream play yeah
where you're like it's so clear but then
you're gonna describe it and it seems so
clear that it be you'd think that you
would remember it all the time but it's
got this yeah beating people but you see
you're coming back to memory yeah huh oh
yeah but but obviously you have to come
back to memory because that's what it is
and and that that's how Debbie died and
others misunderstand purposefully you're
not hiding it
um because hiding it is not about
destroying and a grand narrative and
blah blah blah
it's if you destroy the grand narrative
there's no memory then you were just you
know cutting off there is no future
without origin for Heidegger the other
beginning has always already been
possible is always already there the
arrival of being in all of that that
that's just a way of again ecstatically
let him go of that which is familiar but
then out of that arises new if you like
is everyone you horizons a torn open
but those new horizons are never this
kind of you know progressive idea of
everything just getting better every
year or or the dystopian and
everything's gonna get terrible no it's
it's coming out of something that's
there the other beginning you speak of
an other beginning the other beginning
is is related to the first beginning you
can't have one without the other
yeah that's why he has to go through all
of it again but he's not going through
it and in the sense of you notice
describing it as Hegel would do as a
dialectical process of and this is very
very crudely put so you know all
Hegelians please forgive me but that
there is a thesis and antithesis and it
all comes together in synthesis and we
are marching towards freedom know
there's something else at stake it's
that hiding is this is one of the
strangest notes he says that the history
of metaphysics or metaphysics itself but
not Isis and I'm not a sphere reason
as abstract ideas or so that's now upon
us this is what we now have to face up
to and if you think of it as for example
why is it that we speak of ideas the
word there just means appearance the
Greek word idea where we get the word
idea from just means appearance but it's
become over the centuries this you know
the word idea is the the economy is
driven by ideas or we live in a and idea
economy we live in a knowledge economy
everything everything is actually
extremely abstract idea is a much more
concrete than everyday worlds we live in
which are legalistic and you know very
technical and for Heidegger to
understand technology and find exits
from it it's a actually technology comes
from a certain way that in which
metaphysics has responded to that which
is yes and and what we're trying to do
is we're trying to in betraying to hold
you can look bring this back to death
we're trying to hold on to that which is
because we devour it we desire it sorry
want to devour it
the will is very strong right and ask
but as you know time officially at least
is only passing it's happened as it
needs to be brought back again and be
brought back back again and back into
presence and back into presence and how
do you do that well you do that by
producing hash denim denim placing
positioning the ever same all the time
all over again
yeah so how do you get to consumer goods
perfectly into an exchangeable because
the will wants to have full presence and
control of that which is so we're
producing exchangeable goods right if
they're not really good seni more
there's nothing good about the but that
just see she's here yeah
I mean this this is finding what's
happening in modernity this is
ultimately what technology is after is
that it produces it must produce things
at will that that are always already the
same as something else they're over
there perfectly ever same turning
circling around themselves right yes
right
do you remember and they're sorry that's
the shadows in the cave yeah I mean if
you if someone reads the cave with some
you know some mental capacity and does
it and it doesn't hit them right that
what what's being described there is our
world it's not you know some educational
tool to explain the theory of forms
oh no it's it is we are trapped in the
cave yeah the
how do we what's what's the exit yes
indicate the exit isn't a leaving of the
cave at least you always have to go back
exactly yes yeah it is it's exactly it's
exactly not leaving the case right
that's the strangest thing is that the
shadows that I keep telling my students
you know yours they're usually your
students being duty do you teach like in
a class are you like what do you got
yeah yeah private students and I have I
teach in the class and everything yeah
no it's a look at the shadows are real
yeah right look they're not not that's
just nothing later doesn't say the
shadows aren't real yeah he doesn't say
the cave isn't real sheds are real
they're really there and they're not
just there they're also structuring the
world of the of the people in the cave
of the prisoners yeah so and get that so
a couple things there's one experience I
had with you where what did by the way
the thing that when you said ah you're
using memory again and there's this
muffin what like it that whatever that
feeling is I had of like oh yeah was
just using memory there that except that
experience that's that is that's exactly
what we call circling is etching that
fat like part of getting someone's world
is catching that background but but
because background for me and you called
it out there's that moment of like
ecstatic kind of doom to do to engine
jet totally the same after that you know
and I'm wondering if in a certain way
like for me the memory was like the
shadow in the cave and then you kind of
shined you brought me into the light and
then and then when I saw it I was back
like shadow with the print is that is
that a good well that's that's how
Heidegger says you know you you have to
leave the cave yeah because only when
you
left the cave you can see the shadows as
shadows that they don't light up as
shadows before yeah so bye-bye always
being in that you know continuous
struggle and strife between that which
is down there that which is out there
and coming back down into it then
there's and I this is why you know that
this conversation is as any good
conversation it is a continuum would you
call us Reckling which is a hermeneutic
circle which is almost like a spiral but
it's yes statically working through us
and then bringing something back that
that that's that then because you know
if you are on a time line then it's in
the past
anyways we're in ideaa an hour ago you
said this but it's actually it's always
it's if there's anything to expand
equality in non you know theoretical
terms it's been working it's at that
mentioning of memory at the beginning of
this conversation it had to begin
somewhere work itself through what we're
talking about so because what we're
doing is we're always memorizing
memorizing so we can be memory
remembering we are remembering what
we've talked about and making leaves to
the next topic or feel or ground that's
occurring and showing itself and we're
trying to make sense of what's just
shown itself to us and that sense but
with that that only works by by real
like genuine memory which isn't which
isn't exactly what how we think of it
now which is you know storing data
yeah we're information on some on some
computer or a cloud or whatever it stays
but it's actually it's working itself
through us and through the medium of
language and and this is also why we've
we've given example you've given
examples off of your childhood the
suburbs and I've talked about where I
come from I've talked about my
experience in in the US but look these
aren't just data
points right these are not like oh look
here's a here's a piece of data that can
just throw this it's like if it's just
data's just a given Asst then it's
meaningless yeah it needs to be it's not
because it's not the data just literally
literally just means given right it's a
data battle but it isn't it's actually
not given it needs to be rested from
some some place and then being brought
back to light and then you have a proper
conversation or dialogue or something
lights up that then maybe even you
didn't see yourself before right right
exactly exactly at lining up
is it there's this there's a I think in
taco not being in time but time and
being like is a later work yeah
inning where he talks about I I read
this a lot it's in the beginning of some
of the courses that I do where he talks
about like perhaps it's a good idea if
we not like demand immediate
intelligibility and he says it about you
know yep the artist and then the poet
and then like Heisenberg's formula and
then he says something about like you
know and perhaps it'd be a good idea
well he says like this he says I think
it's this one like sentence and I have
been thinking about for 20 years
literally and I I don't it like a it
eludes my grasp but if it keeps calling
to me right and I still don't quite
understand it but I think I'm getting a
little hint of it as we're talking where
he says let me give you a hint on how to
listen right and for first of all just
that part right which is that there's
not just listening there's ways to
listen right yeah yeah exactly yeah
no because is interesting right because
ears aren't just on take you know tools
to accept and receive sound waves yes
but this is how we think of them on
Tisha I have a friend from Vienna mo
says in arrears and just on dishes on
tisha substratum and then I've just on
take substrate a parrot machines for
hearing their ways of listening yeah
there are ways of seeing and and you
know it's always disliked being eclectic
multi-dimensional if you like that's a
that's I mean that kind of that that
we're on the threat of reduction yes but
right he says he says let me give you a
hint on how to lick listen to the
lecture yeah
exactly what is something like um
instead of listening the lecture of the
series of propositions yes dad we can
begin to follow the movement of showing
yeah to follow the movement of showing
if we refrain and how I how I understand
that is it's like so to listen to you in
a suit like it to translate you or to
hear you with the series as a series of
is is you delivering a series of
propositions on some level I already
have to have the proposition right to
then line it up or not line it up like
there's this kind of quality of there's
a box of intelligibility that I'm gonna
maintain and I can either agree or
disagree yeah well I think what he's
saying is what I'm hearing is like yeah
if there's first of all this is not easy
but if you can basically refrain from
that right something else begins to show
itself right and here's the question
this is what I think I want to like
understand because I'm summable I feel
like this is what I've been the only
thing I've been interested in but I
don't understand it totally it will get
a little it eludes my grasp follow the
movement of showing like what do you
I just curious what are you hearing that
then some level this conversation feels
like things are showing themselves right
and it does well it were yeah there's
yeah you're right you're exactly right
what you presents before there was that
sense of if you even said it's
interesting you did it in in explaining
it right that's right what I read it
back and remembering this and you're
remembering that I said remembering it's
like this these lingering things that
then kind of bit then something opens up
it shows this I'm like oh that's like
and then you pour more wine and you're
like
imagine are we doing that right now it's
just they were doing it but but look
this this is imagined the hell I live in
okay but uh it's it's I think just it is
ecstatic in that sense that it it takes
you out off what is ordinarily there and
into that that which properly is and
when hiding assesses in time and being I
mean he just isn't in most of his public
talks are you could think of for example
the the technology si but the question
for technology where he's very
repetitive to yeah he's very repetitive
but he's always coming at it from a
different angle and then bringing it
back out again and it isn't so much
about a propositional there are no
claims there are no arguments if you
like you right
I mean hiding has a a short note that it
will not be published that was sent out
from the Heidegger Society a couple
years ago on algo mental and I think he
understands argument in in a sense of
lighting up of lighting something up of
showing um and so what what he does I
think you cannot formalize it so I can
only give you another hint at what's
happening it's that Heidegger is I think
very aware of of what's going on of
where it might be coming from of
concealments in history and if you are
aware of concealments you are in and I
sometimes have to stop myself you know
because then you see well this sounds
almost like a cliche but you you see
where others wouldn't even look
but in its a and it isn't as because I
said before there is this good presence
that comes about from ecstatic
temporality that then you can enter by
reading and rereading these texts for
example so that the this showing is
exactly you know it's it's bringing it
back out what's there anyways
but hidden this is why I'm you can think
of it as and this is not my idea this is
my supervisor let me get the statement
was written you know in in in spirit of
Heidegger a book on aesthetics where he
says that metaphor is misunderstood by
us in the West we think of metaphors you
know just just an image did you give to
illustrate something yeah yeah Lisa's
metaphor I'm the Greek literally just
means to to bring some metaphor rain I
think means to bring to bring something
out and about and up which is there but
hidden covered over absconding absent
right but and this is what Heidi
goodness but he sees and this is why you
know I said in the beginning also that
what Heidegger I think is always doing
he's trying to liberate or not liberate
but show access from the Cartesian
matrix that which is that you know the
subject object that caught to me where
we are divided from the world and from
not explain to show no because look if
you explain then you are literally I
don't know there's a short story by Ian
Foster yeah I don't know if you've heard
of I've heard of the name I'm sure I
probably wouldn't yeah I think it's from
from 1912 I'm making this up very very
old more than 100 years old called the
machine stops it's a short story where
people live underground in isolated
cells in the only way they have contact
to each other is via what he calls a
tablet
yeah and we would call zoom or a Skype
these days so they you know they Skype
with each other a faced file this is how
do you go can you imagine yeah oh yeah
you're talking about this one of your
videos yes okay now I'm calling yeah all
he talk all they talk about is ideas huh
how they talk about ideas and they
discuss ideas so you can you can you
know the best is strange that that's the
strange thing about abstraction and
rationality is that it can trap you and
you have it you know you got it all
figured out intellectually but it
doesn't actually mean anything but it is
about Heidi get at the end of his life
there's a there's a conversation that's
on YouTube now um between him and we had
with Sir Richard dresser who is a
documentary filmmaker and he says said
he has I have made an experience in my
thinking that's what he says at the end
of his life an experience in my thinking
right this is something this is not what
Quine would say why would we have to
formalize everything yeah yeah questions
okay impossible it's you know it's he's
not he's not imagining some some future
that should be possible it is actually
for him an experience that that that if
you listen and then let it be like let
something be shown to you not from him
as an authority figure but something
that's phenomenology right something
that shows itself from itself as but all
she needs or what does or is then then
something else
lights out were shows itself that to a
certain degree was there but not not
given but was there in the sense that in
the moment of of it lighting up it
becomes it's it's really there it's
really present and then it becomes
possible and also in the sense of in the
tremana means moved moogly that means
and that comes for Heidegger at least
understands it as coming from Moo
which means to like to love so there's
there's a new new way opening up for for
loving a certain way of being that it
wasn't there before so if you just
engaged in it intellectually or you know
in that sense how we think of it as
philosophy has become institutionalized
everything's become institutionalized um
then you're just trapped again and in
because so much of thinking now is
thinking is schemas and representations
and associations you know you know this
reminds me of innocence good like that
and it's going nowhere right you you
mentioned the word autism before I mean
it is a literal autism huh yeah yeah I
mean or or to speak in the Greek sense
it's idiocy here's the idiot
that's idiot or why it means someone
just for himself circling around himself
yeah but but not but but precisely not
coming out into the world this is where
you yes this is what we have to do you
know it's interesting because I I think
this is what I'm it seems it seems that
it seems to me that I get it when when I
can see it like in it there's that and
you've been I've been spend is my hands
that you really use your hands so it's
like here it's like you're thinking
you're you're it's it's not in your head
you're I could feel as I'm listening to
you I can feel my my sense of embodiment
and my guess like there's a kind of
leaning forward and I just there's
something going on in the body and a
very visceral right yeah what I think is
so exciting for me or ecstatic is that
and this is why I have a question about
this about yeah Alethea right
Alethea so I always thought that like
Alethea when I first started reading
Heidegger I thought ilithyia was the
like is the event of on concealment
right yeah and I thought that it was a
what was the the what was unconcealed
what was lit up yeah I've been thinking
about it like my if I look at my
experience of it it's actually I I it
seems to be less about what was revealed
but in some way more about I don't mores
the right way um but more about
concealed miss was revealed like yeah
like yeah like a good example of this is
like if you watch the movie The Sixth
Sense right where you know it's like the
movie of it is Bruce Willis and he's
dead the whole time but you don't know
it's alright the end neither does he and
of course you know when I went to the
movie my ex my ex-wife knew it she
always knows that stuff but like
everybody else in the theater including
me didn't know it and he's dead and you
at first the movies odd but then the odd
disappears right like and then and then
as the movie unfolds right at the end of
the movie he doesn't realize he's dead
right like yeah you don't realize he's
dead and then just out of the corner of
his eye something all of a sudden he
recognizes it and you had this sight
like everybody in theaters
simultaneously recognizing oh my god
he's dead he's and you get this
experience of he's dead so that's
revealed but oh god here here comes the
memory part but then what happens is the
moment he realizes as he's dead everyone
else does it goes back to the very
beginning of the movie and it shows core
frames in it and you see he was it was
obvious the little time but the mood
right the mood that was a vote it wasn't
it couldn't it doesn't it can't be
reduced to that like oh I didn't realize
he was dead and now I see he's dead and
now I can see that he's dead
no what you actually see is that you
didn't see it right and that's the
ecstatic I don't know I don't know it's
quite quite how to put it but that's
always I've noticed because like a lot
of times like in my work and stuff like
that there's those moments of where it's
not
people it's not people it's not funny
it's like it's these these these deep
experiences that people have of like
whoa like seeing everything the content
of what seemed seems like in fact in
fact oftentimes the content of what
seems content like the cook is usually
awful it's like oh my god I've like turn
the whole world into my mother and been
trying to save her he's like it's not
it's not good news
but yeah healing is one of like almost
like a like an ecstatic like a hot like
an ecstatic countenance of some kind of
like a and I've been thinking about that
was like I I'm wondering about is is
that what Heidegger means right when he
means the event of truth right like that
that the the thing about concealment
like it just feels like it seems to be
more about concealment and that
precisely maybe post modernity it like
was like just to completely forgot about
the concealment on some level they made
it in a project right and then and it
became all about the revealed right yeah
no sense of the mystery of it or the
mood of yeah there to show itself to us
that it's it's there hidden and we can
be aware of that hiddenness is and had
that guide us it might am I making sense
yeah yeah yeah no I did this is to bring
this back to when we talked about for
example technology and it's I mean just
just I forgot the name of the the
director of the sick of the sixth sense
but yeah it's a Bruce Willis is that I
don't know I don't think he's the
director he's the main character yeah
the director made a lot of movies that
are quite a few movies that are you know
playing with what's there and what's not
there and what's hidden and what could
be and what isn't and so
and it also shows you that film is in
hiding google disagree is an ecstatic
art form yes but what over behind a gap
what's always already been forgotten is
Fabio and concealment but also the
absconded of being and in the epoch of
technology and this is so this is not
just a pure model problem for him this
is also problem of or something that
that we inherit from Greek what Greek
thinking and so we stick with the
present as that which is perfectly given
and this plays out in in the sciences
are in the Natural Sciences especially
as you know you find something you have
you have a certain data set and that's
it that's nature we find we found the
gene I mean they've moved the strange
thing is also though that the scientists
keep moving away from their own findings
right once they found something this is
it we this is the human genome that's it
but they're kind of moving away from the
gene theory now yeah that's the kind of
like movie Auto we can't really find the
the gene that makes you stupid because
there isn't yes so it's gonna go
somewhere else i mean i you know unleash
it this is just very maybe not a good
example but nietzsche was supposed to
have had syphilis and that's why he
collapsed right and now they found
something else is the reason and i said
to someone who's you know
Anitra scala i said same zone ten twenty
years ago thirty years ago everyone
believed it was syphilis that got him
that made him collapse and Torino back
then and and I said now it's something
else right and it sounds something in
his brain or whatever and he said yes
this is where science stands down I said
stem so what are you gonna say to me in
ten years time when they think you know
when they find out it was something else
and he said you know this is just how
science has moved on and found something
new so this is literally how you know
it's just always finding something new
than you oh we found something you were
it's completely and forgetting that
which has been concealed by that new
finding it's just programmed into the
entire story right right
so what hiding is as in the let's on
humanism for example is he said it might
just be that nature does not show
herself to the modern or our machines or
apparent Paris to our tools have used in
order to to bring out the wrists the
results of design from from nature and
to a certain degree you know we're all
transcendental idealists or all contents
because we find something that we hip
hypothesize yes but it's it's not just I
mean when it comes a thing of it it's
also mind-blowing least range the epoch
we live in imagine there are Greek
thinkers thousands of years ago will
talk about the optimist
I'm the indivisible particle and then we
go about all just let's just split the
atom and set free vast amounts of energy
were there there's a gentleman called
Hicks who who was at my alma mater at
King's College London who dreamt up the
Higgs particle and then they find it in
the mountains of Switzerland in the
stern I mean just just to give some some
honest I mean hint it and what might be
happening yeah and you know what you've
described about concealment is that
concealment is forgotten but but but but
forgetting is forgotten as well so
they're always double concealments
happening this is why I gave this you
know strange example of Nietzsche and
Nietzsche is a beautiful example here
because you know first it syphilis now
it's a brain tumor and ten years it's
something else but then we'll be fine
because we've moved on so we can forget
about what we didn't understand their
first place and the simplest truth about
Nietzsche's collapse would just be to
exact and that's unbearable for the
modern subject but to accept that needs
collapses why because it you collapse is
because of thinking he collapses because
everything that was ever you know that
that's worked itself through and in
concealment through the history if you
like of metaphysics broke out within him
that's why he collapses he doesn't yes
he Colette the cause you could say is
that a horse is being beat but then he
he didn't come back to life for eleven
years and then he died in in he was you
know out of out of himself for the rest
of it
he many read his notes at the end of it
he was just in a frenzy because he's
also the seismograph of modernity he
sees what's coming right right and but
that that to say that makes you it is
officially something that's considered
madness right if I say that then I'm
considered idiotic and mad and someone
who you kind of possibly mean that
because we we know it was syphilis no it
was the brain tumor but what's working
through all of this is trying to reveal
something is that this is really it look
we can we can latch onto this we can
grasp it we can categorize we can define
and we can we can have it in our hands
and hold it tight but once it slips away
we forget that it slipped away conceived
we conceal the we forget the concealment
and come up with something new and
something else and so the the way that
Alethea ilithyia is is the fundamental
the fundamental thought of Heidi's
entire philosophy if you like that's
that's where it all is because it's it's
it's at once that which reveals or comes
into its own and then forgets itself and
self conceals and absconds and
subscribes and thinking that thought all
the time that and it's you can't even do
it with the hand movements because it's
literally all at once
that's what he calls F Agnes the be
announcing the event of truth of and
this is well then the Uyghurs is also a
realm where the human being and being
meet and encounter age and there are
always consumed ants at work and without
thinking concealment there you you will
never I think with little differently if
if if one begins to consider concealment
sin and absences and moments of
absconded that's all of them strangely
enough that's when something lights up
but that's when the world begins to
light up in a very different way but it
but it but it lights up in a way that it
makes sense right
tired so yeah and has this strangeness
to it yeah
yes but it's all about you mentioned
meister eckhart right before was a
beautiful quote by a cut where he says
I'm gonna say in German first I don't
get house behind here why do you go out
to return home yeah that's that's that's
it that's what we do this is we have to
go out into the world and into the
uncanny into strangeness but but but why
not not to stay there but right I'm back
because a sense of home and arriving you
can only have that sense or no sense yes
by by knowing what what it means to not
be home these moments there everywhere
whether you're thrown into the world you
didn't choose yourself it's flying it's
a come home because you're not home yet
right totally
yeh couldn't have even have earned it
yes Wow
and I think maybe no the sixth sense I
haven't seen it in a long time I I
probably should what I'd probably saw it
before I started reading idea properties
I should probably watch it again it
might be that we know knowingly or not
that what he's trying to do there is to
to to show that in a you know in a story
it's not about Bruce Willis being dead
or not it's about how does concealment
work that something's right
lingering but not showing it's of it but
I mean this yeah but does it look the
strange thing is and I have this I get
this you know responds quite often that
if someone actually listens because what
people would listen but if someone tries
to listen we have a proper conversation
which means to listen and then to
respond and then I hear often you know
something just lights up all of a sudden
yeah when the reason is I think very
simply by fully or not fully but but by
trying to embrace concealments be once
that happens once you think more in
those terms malign up yeah it may really
make sense because again the shadows are
in the cave the shadows are concealed
there concealed in the sense they're
very present yeah they're so present
they make up the world of these
prisoners they're totally happy with
that right they're concealed as what
they are
so by someone who's sort of become aware
of that concealment you can come back
down and see these shadows for what they
are so you see it always it needs that
double movement at least of concealment
unconsumed and disclosure enclosure yeah
you then point to something that is but
as we know from Plato's cave the
yes that the punishment for that is
death this to I it's funny I just had
this like one of the things that clicked
is you we've been talking about this oh
yeah in some way like to become pregnant
he said become present to the
concealments right yeah yeah actually I
what I heard of that is that almost kind
of like can make it your task to
actually become present to them and
what's interesting is like I just kind
of thought this the sense of like and
then he started talking about real
listening and then I was like oh you
know I've been wondering about this
because it seems like that like
metaphorically speaking your eyes can
see what's concealed but they can only
see surfaces right if you look at it
just mechanically yeah but hearing right
I by knock on the desk right what I hear
is that is is what's campus and like I'm
wondering about it listening good yes
exactly but you know attunement to
conceal yeah yes look let me knock okay
we hear the silence after the knock this
is what he talks but that's alloys
destiny the ringing of silence that's
why hearing and listening is so
important and Heraclitus speaking of
backgrounds you know Heidegger says that
he had especially towards the end of his
life ever more the sensational
Heraclitus was standing behind him he
mentioned background right that's he
could think of it as that who's behind
me that and for him it was Heraclitus
and what we've you know categorized as
the first fragment of Heraclitus in 19th
century scholarship
is Heraclitus speaks of logos and I'm
not saying that logos is this you know
fantastical regulating principle of the
universe but logos is Heidegger
transcends logos as original primordial
gathering it's what brings all of us
sort of into in attunement all right
that's what the logo that's that's
that's a buttload so it's not like logos
is here and it does this it that what we
call logos is that which is why you have
to use that is that which excuse us to
gather yeah right
and now Heraclitus says this is how you
get an unsubstantial way of thinking
just point this out i Heraclitus says
that you know people are always already
hearing or our anus certain stance
towards logos but they're not hearing
logos are cooing they're not hearing it
so it's not about reading the logos
right in it and then it's just about
hearing that primordial origination or
occurrence of gathering that then brings
us again then could light something up
but it's important that it's not hearing
it's if you if there's not hearing then
there's always there's already a
concealment at work as well right and
that consumer however if it's sort of
paradoxically focused on and then I mean
logically this makes no sense right
because if you say if I focus on there
to conceal them actually I'm concealing
it but we don't care about that so but
but then it lights up as as as that then
all of a sudden we get attune to that
which is I mean this is how you can only
put it and again you knock on the table
and he'll hear the silence yeah yeah but
he hear it after there was something
there that's then lingering into
to the presence it's like music it seems
it seems well yes I mean exactly so a
live orchestra yeah it is the best one
of the best examples maybe to to show
what would thinkers like Heraclitus and
Heidegger
who maybe by accident have both names
inside with an age but it's it's a but
the orchestra a classical Orchestra is
tension-filled all right just look at
the instruments most of them are string
instruments yet I play guitar maybe you
play a string instrument a string
instrument is just under a lot of
pressure and tension yeah you have fifty
twenty people thirty people fifty go in
an army in an orchestra however Beckett
admit it maybe it doesn't in insane or
immense tension in the air in the
atmosphere just because they are you
know excited and nervous to play just
the individual members of the orchestra
and so is the conductor who has to bring
all of this together and bring it into
what into harmony yeah so harmony is not
because we have you know we have these
cushy ideas of everything harmony is
just everyone gets along it's all nice
and no harmony is something easy
incredibly difficult to bring about and
if it's brought about it is tension they
could always go wrong I'm just imagine
one of them playing one wrong note and
it all sounds just the tension that's
there but what's so what this is trying
I think to what this can illustrate is
or show us and this is something that we
do is that there is a gathering that's
that's happening there and there's a
proper listening and as I then then
there is a sort of coming together where
as you put it you know before they
exactly is that
the note that was just played is not
lost it's actually coming back in the
next know that I'm taking it to the next
node and taking that song
that's how melody arises I mean a melody
would never arise if the time actually
just passed sorry if time just passed
which is boom boom boom boom yeah how is
how does why would bamm-bamm sound like
I'm not really a nice melody but you
have have a certain ring to it because
the one note is playing again in the
next and coming back up again
that's honey it's a melody see it comes
from what has been yes
moving into well there was like lapsing
into beverages to come forming a present
that's a melody even that's how you can
write music if you think of time just as
passing by have no melody you have no
music this you couldn't you couldn't
even yeah getting you wouldn't have any
sense of who you are and ultimately I
think to make is a bit you know
dystopian this is perhaps where some of
this is going is that if you are trapped
in a fake presence like the Netflix kono
binge watching presence for example you
are know many people describe it they
watch Netflix for 10 hours didn't
remember anything on what they've seen
you see the memory is lacking yeah
but so there is no to certain agreed
melodies melody how harmony true harmony
is lacking from from from our way of
being but just say it again the way that
we can listen to a melody is because the
note that was just played is lingering
on next and in the next in the next and
and that
to certain degrees if you begin to
understand history like that then it you
know phenomena begin to light up and
that means that there isn't some you
know ingenious subject who go look this
is what it's like no it's because
phenomena show themselves from
themselves
if one less them show themselves right
but to do that you have to you have to
let silence ring is it fair to say like
with Nietzsche yeah
like you really did name it like God
like that I think it's Tomlinson he
talked about like he named the Anto
theology of the like eternal like the
the Thea the Theo the the God's eye view
eternal return of the same that the Anto
the innermost view right the the will
write that yeah and there so like the
money being like you know the up surging
of a kind of meaningless will to eternal
record of the same for itself but but it
but it exactly yeah that's what it has
to do yeah but to hear that like I just
it's like what a feat that was to hear
that right before beforehand and I
wondering if it's fair to say that
something like hearing that is something
like this like with it like music if you
slow music down I thought about this a
bunch of like what is that point where
like if you slow music down you can
still hear the rhythm right go down and
at some point it becomes farther
probably far enough away such that you
don't hear the rhythm anymore and then
the found that you hear is not in
relationship to other things because you
can't cool it doesn't linger long enough
yeah I'm wondering if something like
Nietzsche like was able to back up
enough such that like
the shot like that the two beats are the
two melodies like God like this it's
something with his hearing where it's
like he was able to like back up enough
so it where it got close like modernity
the beats of modernity he could hear the
song and then that was his understanding
is that deep is that a fair analogy you
think like cuz I'm often talking about
that that understanding is like oh yeah
like oh I hear the music it's got that
history like oh it makes sense it's got
them yeah no yeah yes very much like you
know you you know is of course I'm Aidid
Jade for a long time and and DJ isn't
you're not using your medium it's your
means your medium you're not actually
making music you're the music is the
medium and in the actual thing you're
making is a move right yeah yeah which
is really cool like that's all I like to
think of it it's like you know cook your
cooking but yeah exactly but I think the
design is key sheeted right being
history it's ultimately a melody that
Heidegger listens to that hiding is clay
right in the distance yeah he responds
to it
and it has its ups and downs in its its
terrible moments and it's it's wonderful
disclosures but it is a melody yes we
were responding to but look I mean you
to you know speculate again why is it
that anywhere you go you hear shitty
music right anywhere you go in any
restaurant any any coffee shop or any
any shop even like au supermarkets now I
play terrible terrible music and music
that that depth that's beginning to
sound like I don't even hear any I'm
trying to distance might as much as I
can you know stay away from everything
and then living some others fear yeah
when you got that like what do you
you're hearing what is it like you know
Led Zeppelin in classical bad classical
music in the background of Walmart's
right like that because yeah yeah
something but now it's just like
everything else but everything that
comes out now sounds the same as before
and there are musicologists if you can
still call them you know
that because I don't even know what they
are who say that we will have lost all
courts in the next 20 or 30 years it
will be three to four probably e E major
you know usually major and a major and
it all sounds the same
I mean why this is good because this is
who we are this is logically circular
which is a different way of so clear of
what do you mean by circular right but
that kind of logical circularity is just
shows you that what's at work is that
what you call that will that just wills
itself why because it wills it self I
mean
Heidegger speaks of the will to power
ask the will to will that wills itself
because it wills itself but that's
almost a quote from Johann Gottlieb
Fichte from a German philosopher who
said that was actually at work as will
it will sit self why because it is so
this is a quote from Victor I mean this
is modernity in a nutshell is a will
that wills itself for the sake of ruling
itself and there is no melody I mean
look it obviously all of this makes
sense then you see why is there a
building that cuts into the heavens it's
called the heart they could have chosen
and and and and and why there is almost
anywhere you go this total bombardment
with non music in non places that is
just made to distract you and it's
something that the will responds to
right that's what it wills because it
because it creates this timelessness in
in timelessness you consume more strange
because you are I don't even know I can
spell it out why that is I think in
these you know timeless realms of the
you give the even though all that you it
like who you are there's this you forget
who you are so you
you buy as much as you can because that
gives you something to hold on so it's
your identity you're buying an identity
right because you have no memory of who
you are and yes and and this is why we
need like we need Auto silence at some
point again right we we need to be able
to listen to silence and and and then a
melody this closes itself that then
gives you sort of that that is it's this
is Heidi I think he he says it a couple
of times that this isn't some some grand
enlightenment moment right this comes on
like Nietzsche puts it on Tufts feed it
comes very silently over you and then it
slowly takes over your entire being and
and I think that that should ultimately
be sort of the the goal of or the aim of
well the purpose of any of this is that
it actually means something in the sense
that it changes a way of being yes yeah
right that sense of yes okay that sense
of it's like where that sense of you
know like you you understand or you were
know it like knowing is you know through
being transformed by what you know like
that sense of like it like an i my
understanding of like with Plato like it
sounds like that you had somebody that
you read Plato like really read Plato
right of where it's like he just like
the nowadays usually read a book and
read Plato like that's not how it was
his oral like it was oral you know to
read Plato is - you got enact it right
there's something about that an embodied
enactment that like you actually don't
agree with it but you what is it it's
like you don't it's not that it's not
that you see
what he's saying but you see in terms
you see the world in terms of what he's
saying right like you see that the world
lights up in that then that changes you
right like that you can't ever be the
same after that on some level like that
seemed a good measure to to know when
you understand something is like I don't
know I'm different you're done for I
can't repeat what it was but I'm like
different like yeah yeah yeah that's it
you're done
hey listen is I have to it's 3:30 here
we gonna go in a long time I have to get
going I haven't I have to go to a
meeting and stuff this was absolutely
awesome it was great you really
appreciate this yeah it was a very good
this is rare for me to have
conversations like this and I mean maybe
it's good that it's real it's like yours
all the time but now it's it and we
should we should keep if you like going
I don't know I probably want to keep
going I do you ever come to Britain or I
haven't in a long time but I mean I I
think I I think I can yeah I'd be
interested in in what you do more maybe
like circling you know that stuff and
yeah how's that actually have some video
of like some of me doing a demo circle
for the thing I'm training with somebody
I can I can send you that yeah yes on
YouTube no wherever it is to send it to
you and then I'll a lot I'll load this
up and I'll say I'll send this to you -
I'll link it to link it to you that
would be yeah that would be good and
yeah just let people know that wherever
you are I I exist maybe they wouldn't
talk to me I don't know absolutely yes
but think something I want to do just
between us and this is not going to be
physical
just go ahead just play I'll stop be
quick